howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guest is the futurist max
borders
max is the founder and executive
director of social evolution
a non-profit organization dedicated to
liberating humanity through
innovation max is also the co-founder of
the future frontiers event
and he's a former editor at the
foundation for economic education
howdy thank you so much for having me
jim hey it's great you know we got to
know each other over the years first
virtually and then we hoisted a few in
austin what a couple of years back
good to have you on the show oh i'm
delighted i wish we could do this in
person and
and hoist a few that way but uh kova is
not letting us do that nor is distance
exactly you know i loved austin silly
and i went out to hear
our kind of music you know americana
music about four nights a week at the
various bars in the
south austin and god damn i'd love to
get back there and do that so you know
once the
pandemic is over we may have a chance to
hoist a few again
i sure hope so great well today we're
gonna mostly although i'm sure as always
the conversation
will go every which way talk about max's
book
the social singularity it's a quite thin
book was about 175 pages something like
that
that range i'd say something like that
yeah yeah before you get to the
copious footnotes and index but it's an
amazingly
rich book you know as people listen to
the show know i do on the order of 10
hours of prep for each episode so
not only do i read the book i go through
carefully and annotate it look up
references all kinds of stuff
the amount of stuff i pulled out of 175
page book may be a new record
so if you want to get into something
deep but readable and short i can
strongly recommend
the social singularity not that i'm
going to agree with everything max says
as you'll hear there's some things i'll
have questions about some things i'll
push back on but hey that's the way it
is on the jim rutt show
well and you know we we have a history
of mixing it up anyway jim but that's
what makes it fun to know you
yeah exactly right and the thing i love
about max and like many of the people
that i
work with even that i disagree with on
some things
is that we respect each other and we
always operate from a place of honesty
and good faith and as long as you're
doing that disagreement can be
very healthy amen i wish i wish the
world
these days would take a leaf from that
book honestly because discourse is dying
at least in this country the mind virus
known as
woke which we'll talk about a few times
through here is really clamping down
on the way things ought to be i mean the
idea of the enlightenment
and universal liberal humanitarianism
just going out the window it's
disturbing as
frankly but anyway let's get down to it
we'll talk about that as we go
first you call yourself a futurist and i
think that's cool
you know if i would do my life over
again i might be a futurist
you know i remember reading the
foundation trilogy
when i was about 10 years old and one of
the central characters who
it doesn't really come on stage as i
recall was harry selden the psycho
historian right who had his formulas for
predicting the future
and of course that's not really what
futurists do you actually had a pretty
cool quote which i'm going to pull up
here
which is we have always tried to know
tomorrow
in our attempts we end up shaping it
which is interesting
talk a little bit about how you view the
role of the futurist
well i think most of the time futurist
is a marketing label that people slap on
themselves
in the hopes of trying to sell a book or
get a talk and i certainly fall into
that camp
but but if you were to look at it in
terms of uh other
circles of a venn diagram that
participation in the creation of the
future is really
an aspect of it that i think is is quite
important
you know there's a thing called a
self-fulfilling prophecy
and self-fulfilling prophecies you know
have that has a good connotation and bad
connotation depending on
the content of whatever it is that is
the prophecy
i like to think of myself as an optimist
even though i'm
becoming increasingly pessimist with
things i see around me in the world and
we
we're going to talk about that as you
say but i try to remain
optimistic for a couple of reasons and
you really i hope see that or found it
in the book jim
but this notion of an optimistic
self-fulfilling prophecy
i basically get to surf on trend lines
and find the ones that are favorable to
human flourishing
point those out and write about them in
what i hope is pretty prose
and that is you know the extent of my
futurism
i believe in the power of belief
and what we're seeing right now in terms
of
as you as you suggested earlier you know
the woke
sensibility is perhaps a negative
example of that but what this book tries
to lay out
is a more liberal cosmopolitan
sensibility for possibilities in the
future
yeah well very well said essentially i
think you said that
as you create you're pointing possible
ways for people to
think about what the alternatives may
actually be and you go pretty far out in
this book which i like
you know i often point out to people how
influential something as
prosaic as star trek was a mainstream
commercial tv thing from the 60s
it's amazing the amount of ideas that
came out of star trek which actually
pulled people forward towards the future
you know i definitely respect that role
so
next the title the social singularity
what are you trying to convey with that
title well
it's i think most of your listeners are
going to be familiar with
kurtzweil's thesis of the technological
singularity and actually
kurzweil is really he's really borrowing
from
other really great thinkers verner vingo
was one of the
science fiction writers you might be
familiar with that
harkens to the future with some of his
science fiction writing
and then if prior to that an old
computer scientist
whose name escapes me really laid out
some of the idea that
in some at some future point the
machines will essentially wake up
yeah good was his name good thank you
yes
and this sort of trajectory of thinking
parallels the development of of computer
science
really and of ideas in
in sci-fi when you start to see this
pattern it becomes really meaningful
in the sense of predicting the future
and of course folks are probably
familiar with kurzweil's variation of it
which is to extrapolate from moore's law
you get a doubling of computing power
every roughly 18 months
and that moore's law effect that
trajectory appears in
other kinds of technological advance
whether that's
storage battery power all kinds of
effects but there's essentially this
amazing swelling of computer power
going into the future and that the
propagation of
ideas i believe happens in this way so
but i wanted to with this book hearken
to that and say hey but that's not the
only
pattern into the future that's seeing
this level of progress and improvement
the way we interact with each other as
human beings the the way we can use
technology to lateralize our
relationships
can also have a similar trajectory in
terms of
how we collaborate how we work together
how we improve our collective
intelligence
and so on so these forces
moving into the future i guess you could
say
allow us to have a parallel track to the
technological singularity which is
the social singularity and that's a
really humanistic frame
for if i could write a parallel book to
any number of books about the
technological singularity like the age
of spiritual machines
it would be this book and it's to say
hey we've got these
other we are developing human practices
and protocols
that will allow us to be both more
pluralistic and yet more unified but
also more
advanced in the what's possible to
create
together yeah here's a quote from your
introduction
i think suggests that but not maybe
quite as much detail
you write i suggest that if we
reorganize ourselves in our systems
collective intelligence
will be better as a species the social
singularity is a point beyond which
humanity will have reoriented itself
will operate more like a hive mind
kind of interesting a hive mind not what
i would expect a libertarian
quasi-anarchist to say
well that's interesting that you point
that out i try to
explain in the book that we want to stop
short at least at this point of thinking
of us
as a single unified noaa sphere
okay some kind of woo-woo concept of a
super brain
not quite going there what i'm trying to
hearken to there
is the idea of programmable incentives
and the possibility of coordination that
is possible
in let's take the example of starlings
and murmuration
okay or of small fish i guess
they would be anchovies swirling to
avoid the big tuna that come up under
the sea
this synchrony of movements that you see
in some species that allow them to
defend themselves that allow them to
organize their efforts requires a
certain kind of simple protocol
and these have been you know since the
70s and 80s
this kind of synchronous behavior has
been programmed
with fairly simple algorithms that give
rise to this
highly complex state of affairs and you
know all about this gym given your
involvement with uh complexity science
so the idea that we can have protocols
that organize uh collective or
collaborative behaviors
is really the essence of what i'm trying
to pull out of that
but that's not to say that every single
decision or every single phenomenon
needs to be unified in some weird
collectivist
borg brain but rather we can have
different programmable incentives in
different communities of practice
that allow us to coordinate and
collaborate at scale but these may
compete with each other these may
be towards different ends we say telos
which is you know the greek for end
so our goals may be different from one
to the next but the possibility of
collaboration at scale is
is becoming a phenomenon that's getting
closer and closer
and indeed our collective intelligence
in the way we measure it through
programmable incentives is also starting
to become more and more promising and
i can talk a little bit about the
collective intelligence aspect of that
too
uh in a moment but just think about
the way market prices coordinate
behaviors from people
in different times and places and
even disparate cultures around the world
it's really staggering the kinds of
flow systems that are possible based on
the simple price system
it doesn't include all the information
but it includes a lot
it's really information wrapped in
incentives and prices
function to really are at the center of
a global ecosystem of
flows of value those can be interrupted
of course those can be
changed but the market is itself a
species of collective intelligence
so the the liberal anarchist in me
is happy with that notion but the idea
of a hive brain
is also in there that we can collaborate
at scale towards
ends that we happen to share as a human
community
yeah very good i mean i would kick it up
maybe one level of abstraction which is
that
for sure collaboration is one of the two
or three human super powers you know we
collaborate better
and in more detail and more ways than
any other species
and to do collaboration is pretty much a
commonplace of information theory and
complexity theory
there's got to be some way information
flows so i call them signaling systems
and so i think what you're talking about
is a specific point of view
on how do we upgrade our capability for
collaboration
using a set of signaling systems which
you describe and
i would again say the abstract is a
little higher level incentives is one
form of signaling system but there may
be other signaling systems
may not have to be incentives right i
mean one could imagine
in kind of a nightmare dystopia that the
signaling system was literally right
into your brain made you do things right
that actually might work quite well for
collaboration but i'd hate to know who's
in control that right
my kid is aware of uh you know certain
kinds of incentives
a lot of them are the the term
incentives can be financial but it can
also be
you know psychic rewards of certain
kinds my kid is a
it's a gamer a gamer kid he's a he's
kind of an addict
and i'll admit that on the show and i
don't know what i'm going to do about
his
his proper education but at least he's
good at all the games
now this kid understands incentive
systems in terms of psychic rewards
he he understand you know he's actually
tried to tell me dad you need more
if as i've been trying to develop
certain kinds of technologies
for for uh collective intelligence he's
like dad you need more badges you need
more you know gamification elements
you need more things that allow you to
to
be perceived as higher in the pecking
order like leaderboards
these are all things that have been done
but my my kid understands this
intuitively because he's 13.
there are also things that's like how do
we know that we're helping someone how
do we become more
empathic how do we know that the things
that we're claiming are true
are actually true as in
verified in terms of some
mind-independent reality so there are
other kinds of um you know they're uh
incentive systems
that might help with the the truth or
falsity or something
but there are also systems that may not
depend at all uh
and i think you have if you've not
already had arthur brock as a guest
i have twice i'm gonna go back and
listen to that because he has a
fantastic view of the different kinds of
ways we can see currency
and i think if he discussed that on the
show yeah i did two episodes with him
one about
polo chain and the closely related
technologies
and then i did another one which we just
recently published that we talked to him
and fernanda his associate about
currencies in the abstract and that was
extremely
interesting and again that's where we
get to the idea that signaling systems
can be all kinds of things right
that's right that's right one more point
about that quickly because
i don't want to give the impression that
the social singularity is a
call for us to create a series of
skinner boxes for ourselves even if
they're different skinner boxes
human beings are more than just
creatures that
respond to stimulus and response you
know there are
a lot of endogenous capabilities about
us
as complex beings that are important to
understand
as we seek to form community but
starting with incentives is a good place
to start we just have to be
very careful how we do it very well said
now one of our signaling systems for
collaboration
you bring a harsh spotlight to and
that's politics
politics says it currently exists
particularly in america but i think
you're
critiquing political infrastructures in
the advanced democracies more generally
here's what you actually say about them
politics brings out the worst in us by
tapping into tribal tendencies
sure trading barbs is better than
trading bullets we all know really nice
people
who participate in stinging and
acrimonious exchanges online
maybe we do it ourselves and you further
comment that particularly the american
political system
and some of the others around the world
tend to collapse
individual ways of relating to the world
into a single dimension which ends up
with two teams team red and team blue
you're onto something there what more
can you say about politics as a broken
signaling system for collaboration well
and there's a there's a lot of
dimensions to how it's broken uh there's
a there's just
there's so many reasons why our
contemporary
political system is just utterly
bankrupt in my view and i can't stress
this enough
i i use this metaphor at the beginning
of the book about
the you know waking up one day picking
up your device and finally
finding only two apps the red app and
the blue app
imagine how restrictive and how and and
by the way
neither of these apps works particularly
well
uh and you know the speeds of the apps
are terrible
but the the range of choices is is is
pretty pitiful there
so that metaphor is not only meant to
unpack the problem of the range of
preferences that people might have as
complicated beings
but it's also the fact that it's not
just a matter of those choices it's a
it's the fact that so many of our
preferences get blurred together in the
through the political process
that the outcome of an election
is rarely ever determined by a single
voter
much less yours if i live in a state
that is not a
purple state that's you know one of the
the states that everybody
fights over in elections the chance that
i'm gonna
affect the outcome of a national
election is even more remote
but even then it's i i i to to change
metaphors quickly
the idea of democratic voting to me is
like
shouting at at two teams uh standing on
stage
at madison square garden and expecting
my voice to be heard
or being at a concert and shouting play
free bird
at at a at a rush concert well that
wouldn't work
because not only is it a different band
but uh i'm never going to be heard so
this whole thing about making your voice
heard
is you know it's all just such drippy
notions of civic participation that
actually
don't amount to anything in reality i
think
another problem i mean i could go all
day about this
um jim but i guess i'll i'll button this
point up by saying
you know it's one of the real problems
with democratic voting is that we don't
have any skin in the game
in any meaningful sense the the people
can hold
wild views about things because there's
no immediate
consequence for holding that view and
voter voting is a great example of that
whenever you vote for something and
signal your rectitude or your sanctimony
or your idea of morality
in the voting booth you're not only
crying a teardrop in the ocean and
expecting the tide to turn
but you're also not being
punished for any kind of bad decision
immediately that you can feel
whereas there are different mechanisms
for decision making
and consensus systems that allow you to
feel the sting of loss when you make a
bad decision
democratic voting doesn't do that and i
won't even get started on the problem of
special interests and all that stuff
so we'll get to that one because that's
important right but here's i'm going to
push back a little bit for the first
time
which is you know my position is that
the american
constitution while amazingly brilliant
and prescient in its day
is now quite obsolete and these were
some of the smartest people ever and
it's amazing to
remember that 1776 population the united
states was about 2.5 million
about the same as kentucky right could
you imagine going to kentucky and
finding
james madison john adams ben franklin
george washington
you know the masons on and on and on
these brilliant thinkers so it was
really quite an amazing
you know athens-like moment that this
tiny number of people came up with this
but it's also important to remember 1776
was before
fossil fuels basically yes there was
some cold the uk being
used but there was no coal mined in the
united states until 1804
and the main thing that's happened since
1800 has been a lot of things
but the main thing has been the
intensification of energy
applied to our systems which allowed our
systems to become more powerful
better they tear the out of the
earth all kinds of things
but it mostly comes back to upgrading
our energy density
and 1776 was before that started to
happen
so when i critique politics i step back
a little bit and say
you know is it the fundamentals of what
you call
i thought that was quite funny a
democratic operating system or
dos and i'm old enough to remember when
doss was state of the art
is that fundamental or is it an
institutional problem that we have
and i'm not yet entirely sure that there
aren't better ways
to institute democracy and maybe we
update
from dos to what i'd always thought was
one of the great operating systems of
all time
nt 4.0 that was a microsoft operating
system i guess it was around
the year 2000 2001 which is really
good and way better than
dos not even in the same league and so
yeah let's consider the nt 4.0 versions
of a democratic operating system
you know first pass the post is one of
the things where we you know individual
legislatures are elected one at a time
by plurality
vote in most states a few states have
runoffs but not a lot
what happens if we did proportional
representation like they do in
israel there's a dozen parties that vary
in
multiple dimensions you know what would
happen if we went to ranked choice
voting
rather than vote for one plurality wins
or my favorite and i know you
pooh-poohed it in the book
that's okay liquid democracy where
we each have proxies and in my version
of liquid democracy we each have proxies
for
as many issue areas as we want and then
we proxy our votes to people who we
think
are more knowledgeable than we are so
for instance i might want to
proxy my abortion vote to a pro-choice
organization
and i might want to proxy my gun rights
vote to the nra
right well as it turns out in america
there are almost no politicians of note
who are both
pro-choice on gun rights and abortion
even though from the lens of liberty it
would seem that
pro-choice and pro-gun rights ought to
be together in the same basket
as it turns out our broken institutions
don't allow that to emerge but liquid
democracy does
and it strikes me that the inherent
institutional
aspects of liquid democracy might
actually
reduce this temptation to tribalism
because nobody would be tribal each
person would be
a high dimensional representation of
their own views
and there's some other alternatives you
know one that athens used in the heyday
of
you know the first rise of democracy is
called sortation or they pick people at
random you go what the pick people
at random
well there's been some experiments done
by guys like james fishkin
scholar on deliberative democracy where
you can take people at random put them
through a process which he calls
deliberative democracy where they really
explore an area in detail and it's
probable they'd actually produce better
results than our current broken system
with all of its strange attributes and
veto points
etc so i guess that's my first big
pushback is
are you giving up on democracy because
our institutions are
250 years old and aren't really state of
the art anymore
i don't think there's a binary there i
think there's a lot of
there's a lot of interesting aspects to
this question
and and let me let me click back in
order of magnitude and talk about this
from the perspective of the above
because you started out talking about
the us constitution
i'll push back on you on the u.s
constitution and say i don't think it
needs to be outmoded
i think it needs to be enforced so
that's the first point i'll come back to
that
the second point is i do think that some
of these
rank choice voting liquid democracy all
of these are interesting models
in and of themselves and they would be a
probably a modest improvement but i also
think that they're kind of tinkering
around at the edges so if we were to
pull back to that 30 000 foot
view for a second and look at the system
let's think of it as what is the best
way to have a system of systems
okay which is a pluralism of systems
people who like the idea of equality
before the law may not like this
but we already have it in our in our
federalism now it's just not as
pronounced
because much of the action is going on
at the federal level
that's just what i find objectionable so
first you have this idea
that that there is this monolith that
should be
you know governed over 350 million
people and you're right
that is outdated but the constitution
has provisions
in it that are simply not enforced the
jurisprudence around
for example the ninth and tenth
amendment is just horrible
there is there there's no uncertain
terms
about the kind of experimentation we
could have in
some sort of principle of subsidiarity
that is given to us
in the ninth and tenth amendment now we
could have a constitutional amendment
that made a provision for subsidiarity
but we really wouldn't need it
we have we get most of what we need out
of that
federalism from the ninth and tenth
amendment and it's as if
somebody just took a giant eraser and
took it out of the bill of rights
ninety percent of what the federal and i
sound like an old conservative here and
i'm sorry i'm just going to do that but
from a systems theory perspective
having this monolithic system and
most of what the federal government does
is unconstitutional
not be able to be pushed down to the
level or devolve to the level of the
states
means that we lack tremendous potential
for experimentation
and that experimentation could include
stuff like
different different kinds of voting and
different kinds of uh
you know consensus mechanisms decision
making uh of of all sorts
you know there there are consensus
mechanisms that are coming out of the
the digital ledger community uh that
were started
in uh by intellectuals and they're now
being tried
uh a couple of them are both at george
mason in fact that are really
interesting consensus mechanisms
one is my robin hansen his idea of
futarki i think it's limited but i think
it has some
some things to recommend it and
one of the things that hanson points out
and people like philip
tetlock point out is that when you have
this proxy voting by
experts or you have this you know which
is just
giving giving you democratic tyranny of
expertise
philip tetlock says look experts half
the time don't know what the hell
they're talking about they're just full
of a lot of bluster
you know tetlock's whole metaphor of the
fox and the hedgehog
really does show you the the problem of
expertise
especially in america we have this
tendency to rely to outsource our sense
of responsibility and cognition to
experts because well they're experts but
even experts get it wrong a whole lot of
the time
and so proxy voting and things like that
that allow us to sort of
remove the responsibility for our own
cognition
or our own our own civic engagement
i think is problematic and that's simply
because most
complex problems are too hard for any
single expert or group of experts to
solve anyway
that's not all problems but many
problems
and so the way i like to think about
governance is let's try to let's let's
let a thousand
flowers bloom let's let's try different
experiments in governance
and then we can start to see what works
better and what doesn't
just thinking about switzerland the way
switzerland is designed
in the canton system is i believe
superior to the united states government
but we actually have that enshrined in
the constitution
so whatever ways you want to make
decisions at the local level
where people have a greater sense of
what's going on a closeness to the
action if you will
those kinds of decision-making
mechanisms would certainly be
more appropriate for local elections
and and also uh local referenda
but uh at the scale of widespread
society i'm
i'm not so sure so just to to button
this point up i think the way i what i'd
like to see
is much more experimentation and you can
start
by not having sort of a jurisdictional
monolith at the federal level
yeah and all the writing i've done
liquid democracy i pointed out that
while i believe the ideas are
interesting
and people are interested in a good
place to start check out my essay on
mediums called an introduction to
liquid democracy and it points to some
of the other documents i've written on
it
is that it does need to be tested
because it's a classic
deep theory and it might be wrong right
and so let's test it at the level of
cities or counties before we try it at
the level of states and countries
and i will say this is an area where i
think we're very much in agreement
that subsidiarity sort of smells very
right to the future that you're alluding
to
the social singularity and that other
folks like jordan hall have been working
on i've been working on it my own little
way etc
but again i would push back that the u.s
constitution
even if read as it was in 1929 is still
not sufficient
you know we have all kinds of strange
structural elements in there that are
having to do with disputes about slavery
and everything else well i agree with
that
i mean it is bendable but the the the
way the amendment process designed is
designed is
is problematic and yet it has protected
us from a lot of the liberal action on
the part of
various legislatures over the years so i
i'm with you
to a degree you probably think it's
completely outmoded and scrapped
and by the way jim i have a new book i'm
working on right now and i discuss this
very thing in part two
where i say hey if we can keep the
constitution this is what we need to do
to fix it
and if we can't then i have all sorts of
crazy ideas that are more like what
you'll read in the social singularity
cool we should have you on when that
thing is out it'd be fun oh gosh
i'd be delighted because i obviously i
want to sell a copy or two
yeah i try to normally do these
interviews right when a book is coming
out or has just come out in fact one of
my favorite interviews
will be out in a couple of weeks when
james lindsay's new book cynical
theories comes out
this thing is great i'm
recommending everybody
who wants to see the roots of wokism and
why it is a broken
system of thought that's much closer to
marxist leninism
and nazism than it is to universal
liberalism
really needs to read jim lindsey's book
i highly recommend it
absolutely i i i could not help but
but uh cheer on in second that emotion
um and i just
read an article of his the other day uh
something to the effect of and maybe
this can go in the show notes
something to the effect of why a wokist
won't
engage with discourse in you or won't
have a conversation with you or argue
with you something like that
yeah yeah the reason is it's like
medieval catholicism
it's an unfalsifiable closed her
medically sealed system
where questioning the system itself is a
sin that's right
[Laughter]
so it's ie basically a cult
and james lindsay does an amazing job of
dissecting this in a very calm
dispassionate research-based fashion so
call out the james here but let's get
back to your work here you know again
i'm i'm with you on
subsidiarity in fact that's oddly enough
an old catholic doctrine
you know the idea that every problem
should be
adjudicated with governance at the level
appropriate
and of course in the past where we
didn't have these cool network tools
you know we ended up something like the
us constitution with you know the
federal government the states
and then we have counties and cities but
at least in the u.s
they are creatures of the state here in
virginia for instance we have the very
annoying
thing called the dillon rule which quite
explicitly says that counties
and cities have no rights whatsoever
except those explicitly delegated to
them
by the state so if you want even you
know the ability
to have a municipal power company
in virginia you have to have specific
legislation from the state legislature
do i that seems
nuts to me and so a
fractal system where there can be
multiple layers as appropriate
you know even county and city are pretty
arbitrary geographic and we'll get to
some of your very cool ideas about
geography being perhaps obsolete when we
think about watersheds you know they're
kind of
orthogonal to or at least operate at a
different dimension than cities and
counties air sheds
to what degree do we want to have food
self-sufficiency in a region you know
there's so many different
scales at which social signaling could
and should happen to provide high
quality collaboration
that a more general theory of
fractal self-organization using
some form of social signaling i like
liquid democracy but there could be
others
maybe closer to both of our spirits of
true subsidiarity rather than this
you know two-level model that we
inherited from 1789.
absolutely i i just want to uh extend a
big high five on that one
um i love it we argue a lot and it's fun
but when we have
uh moments of agreement i just want to
relish them for a moment
you know there's um this idea of of a
fractal notion of of governance is
really
important you know if you if you've ever
clicked down in an old mandelbrot
fractal
you can you can just sort of open
another universe of possibility and see
see complete novelty when you do that
and i think that metaphor really extends
to
to life on planet earth uh literally and
figuratively to to the
you know social life of human beings but
as well as to the to the ecosystems and
the way these
these two apparently disparate
systems interrelate but i i wanted i
want to take a moment to
to talk about uh something interesting
there's this
there's this article that that the game
b community and i'm sure your listeners
are now familiar with the game b
community but one of the
sort of seminal articles for the game b
community came from a guy named scott
alexander who's a brilliant fellow
i really love i love his writing
i think it's a man uh and uh so does
everybody else really it's it's just
it's
phenomenal work and he recently had to
shut down his blog because
he was worried he was gonna get uh
cancelled or trashed in his
personal life so he wanted to remain
pseudonymous in any case
scott alexander had this this article
called meditations on molok which is one
of his
a piece that went viral and is you know
really has an important
important lessons about how we can
protect
the environment or guard against certain
kinds of uh
what some listeners might call
existential threats that are a result
of perverse human incentives and and
usually these have to do
with the way property rights are
assigned and that's goes back to the old
you know uh
tragedy of the commons and of course
alexander's aware of the tragedy of the
commons
you know when there when there are no
private property rights
everybody has a race to exploit some re
resource
and of course you know commons problems
can infect
political allocation as well you just
have to know the right politician to be
able to exploit the commons
but it still happens so the the first
nobel prize winner in economics who was
a woman her name is eleanor ostrom
had this great research on
the management of the commons and i
would encourage
folks to look at some of the historical
or and anthropological things that
eleanor ostrom was able to uncover about
commons management
and solutions to these sort of problems
of moloch
and then go back to you know this
general understanding of subsidiarity
and
seeing the sort of fractal development
bottom-up fractal development of system
localized systems of commons management
and i think we'll see
a lot more promise than some of our game
b
community has with respect to these
these problems
you know she really did point out some
of the some things
that can especially if we have a local
evolved sensibility
you know a sensibility towards local
evolved mechanisms for protecting
commons we really can go very far indeed
once we mix that with some of the
technological
inputs that something like holochain or
other
other you know observation mechanisms
for common commons management but also
some of the incentive systems
that can be developed locally for
managing commons there are a lot of
really great solutions here and i don't
think we need to
worry so much about the god malloc
i still worry about the god molech but
three cheers for eleanor ostrom
i recently did an episode with michelle
bowens of the peer to peer foundation
and we talked a lot about the commons
right
and he makes a good point that garrett
hardin's tragedy of the commons was
actually a bad argument that
yes in theory you could have a tragedy
of the commons in a completely
unsocialized
commons but if you look at historical
practice back to you know
medieval shared fields or fishing rights
in
12th century portugal or whatever the
commons
were never just wild frontiers there was
always quite significant
sometimes suboptimal but quite
significant social system control of how
the commons were used and until
we got to the modern age of out of
control unregulated commons the
tragedy of the commons was relatively
uncommon
a few cases maybe easter island but not
too many
and looking at that literature is is
actually very hopeful and a very good
way to think about
a subsidiary related solution you know
particularly for things like
the land water resources pollution
etc and so i think we're sort of on the
same page there but i still do worry
about
malik particularly in a regime where
network effects allow malik even if it's
commercial malic to get
really big yeah i agree with that both
commercial
and and go on the government side i
think the collusion between
the corporations and the state is uh
responsible for having it lock in the
sub-optimal
situation and i think you and i agree i
i want to encourage people to uh for
people to look at your article on
game a to game b transition there's a
lot of really good stuff there um
but yeah i think on that point you and i
agree yeah interesting
let's go on to another topic which you
talked about quite a bit
which is science can't be trusted
i have done a lot of thinking and
reading and talking with people about
what i might call the sociology of
science
and i'm with you part way here and that
there is a lot
in the way science operates in terms of
the funding by the national science
foundation nih the
details of peer review how a career in
science is actually
defined and made fundable etc which
could certainly be
improved and as people listen to the
show know
i've dug in a bit to the unreproducible
result problem which is indeed as you
point out endemic at least in certain
areas of
science in fact we had brian nozick on
the show
one of our relatively early guests who
is the guy who
really started the ball rolling on the
reproducibility crisis particularly in
psychology
who now runs the center for open science
one of my favorite little organizations
if people are interested in
how to fix science just go to their
website about 75 percent of what we need
to fix sciences
right on their website but i would say
this
that if you look at science on a
continuum and of course this continuum
does great violence to a lot of things
that aren't on the continuum
but put physics at one end and sociology
at the other
i think you will find that the crisis of
science
is more on the sociology side of the
ledger than it is on the physics side of
the ledger
and an awful lot of the social sciences
have unfortunately become
politics by another means and aren't
even really science
now we put psychology kind of at the
halfway point and
nozick's work showed somewhere between
35 and 50 percent
of psychology papers are not
reproducible
if you probably got the sociology it
might be a high a lot more than that but
i'll tell you this it's physics
it's the other extremes 95 are probably
reproducible
so i think it's important to realize
that the bulk of this problem is in the
softer sciences not in the harder
sciences sure and i never
argue that the science is uh broken or
irredeemable at all i don't i hope i
didn't give you that impression and i
hope i don't give readers that
impression
what i'm trying to do with that with
that section is really
disabuse people of the scientism strain
both in the soft sciences as well as in
in in medicine for example
they're just a lot and and the id people
will come on you know online with this
bludgeon
science says this or you know
they're even article titles science says
as if science is this god
you know that's personified but but
science is a collection of human beings
that have
biases and cognitive distortions and
operate within different
incentive systems and i just want to get
people to continue to question
expertise in the manner that say karl
popper would have would have liked with
his thesis of conjecture and refutation
we have to think of science as otto
neurot a philosopher had this great old
metaphor for it as
a boat that we're constantly taking
boards off taking apart and putting it
back together while at sea
it's never finished it's never something
that we can just
you know we can all just this is true
and we can all go home it's this
constant process of revision and
skepticism
frequently drives that but you're right
there is a politicization
of saying science is definitive on this
the science has settled moved on it
doesn't matter what the issue is
um and people will use that as a way to
sort of
to shut down conversation or to to shut
down
skeptical perspectives so this is really
you know
a way of showing that disintermediation
in science
can help us with the project of putting
together
uh this mosaic that is this i guess
ever-changing mosaic of scientific
understanding that's really what i want
to get across
not that it's broken and not that it's
irredeemable but that some of the kinds
of
decentralization we're seeing now can
actually help
help us get a more a better resolution
picture of different scientific
subject matter and and areas of
expertise
yeah i will say i think you maybe
weren't nuanced enough at least for my
tastes there
because i do agree with many of the
critiques but i think you hit it several
times and it
could easily leave the flavor of people
being more suspicious of science than
they should be
you know to give a real world example
here probably
relatively soon we're going to have a
vaccine or multiple vaccines for covet
whether one should take it or not is
fundamentally a scientific question
and we're going to have to use some good
collective intelligence
to come to that decision now we had
brian hanley on the show
some time back he actually has already
made his own covid
vaccine he's a vaccinologist and he gave
it to himself
and to a couple of his friends i believe
even though he wouldn't quite say that
and
he seems to think it works i sort of
wouldn't try his vaccine
and so it's important that we have an
appropriate level of skepticism about
science and as you say
in general anyone who said science says
it's true that
is not a scientist right all real
scientists know that science is
contingent that it's an ongoing process
of refinement and asymptotic approach
towards what is probably true you know
that's propery in science as you say you
put forth a
claim hypothesis you test it you find
some results that don't refute it or
confirm it
and then it's good until someone does
refute it and look at the history of
science even
ideas we thought were pretty bulletproof
like newtonian system
of space and time turned out to be only
a first order approximation when
einstein
did his thing in the relativistic space
and then we can stumble into wholly
unexpected domains like the
very peculiar world of quantum mechanics
which we still don't really understand
but we can at least measure it
so in general science does not say this
is true
though there are some things that i
think are so well established that
sometimes we forget to say contingent
like the
earth goes around the sun rather than
vice versa but
for anything that's even close to new we
should always keep in mind
it's got a high level of contingency but
that said
when it comes to whether i should try
the covid19 vaccine
that comes out in february i'm going to
carefully review the science i'm going
to
look for signs of inter-subjective
agreement amongst groups of scientists
that seems well-founded and i'm not
going to pay too much attention to
cranks on facebook exactly i
i couldn't agree more and in fact um
i've been horrified by some of the
anti-vaxxer stuff that's been going on
like i literally had uh you know this
this happens uh you know i
i've tried to discipline myself not to
interact on social media anymore with
people who seem
just beyond help but people who are
really trying to tell me
that you know that medical science
didn't eliminate smallpox
and it's like i you know that look at
look at the trend lines before the
smallpox
vaccine came out it was already going
down well yeah it's because people
learned how to
what germ theory was and how to wash
their hands and how to stay away from
people who have smallpox i mean just
basic public health knowledge
but you know it took it took the vaccine
to really eliminate it from the planet
as
as we've seen and it's just it's
staggering to me this get the level of
skepticism
it goes i go back to this idea uh brian
kaplan
writes about this idea a lot of rational
irrationality
if you have and this is what hap this is
this is the kind of stuff that infects
voters and this is why i think
voting is such a bad idea for as many
people who believe and they could easily
be a majority someday
believe that vaccination is bad there's
very little
direct consequences for holding that
belief well let's just stipulate
that i'm that i'm right and that you're
right jim about
vaccines that they work and that they on
net
make us healthier because they eliminate
deadly viruses
okay the fact that someone has this
false belief
of anti-vaxxer is they're essentially if
even if they don't vaccinate they
essentially free ride on people who do
and nothing happens to them so they come
under this idea
their kids don't get smallpox their kids
don't get measles much unless you're in
california in which case
you know you finally had to eat that
because it was a measles outbreak from
all the anti-vaxxers
out there but at the end of the day it's
like look guys
you know this problem of not having
direct skin in the game for the
consequences of
really dumb ideas is endemic
to the democratic process and in fact it
is endemic to
the people who are making decisions on
our behalf
they don't have any direct consequences
for making stupid decisions in
washington either so i
i i want to bring that that full circle
while agreeing with you that i'm going
to take a good hard look at the
intersubjective agreement
around vaccines for coven 19 because i
sure as hell don't want it and i don't
want my kid to have it
exactly right so this is actually a good
test case
right because in our current world in
particular and it's something we may get
to
if we have time for the first time ever
essentially
unmediated person-to-person
communication on a worldwide basis
seems to be breaking our sense-making at
a pretty high rate
i mean you know anti-vaxxers flat
earthers
the election of an idiot like
trump right how the hell could that
happen
right something seriously has gone wrong
in our sense making and vaccine policies
probably
an interesting test case for some of
your ideas skin in the game what would
be
a max borders beyond the singularity way
to
make a decision about whether the
government should be investing billions
which it is and i think it's a good
thing
on fast tracking vaccines and may even
mandate vaccines
at least for certain things like access
to public schools access to airplanes
access to government buildings
what is a mechanism for making a
decision like that
that could have skin in the game or at
least could have better sense making
attributes than our current system
that's a complex question so i want to
try to disentangle it a little bit
um i may and i want to make sure i
understand the question
one thing i'm hearing is what is a what
is a a social singular
singularitarian way of deriving some
sort of
consensus mechanism for a large group of
people yeah let's break it down
the first question is how do we get
consensus
to invest billions of dollars on fast
tracking the vaccines
or even should we right i mean yeah i
suppose in theory every county could
fund its own vaccine program that
doesn't seem too smart
it seems that the vaccines is a
nation-state level
scale takes billions of dollars and
global so how do we
get to a consensus that we should invest
billions to fast-track the vaccines
right now in the post-singularity world
well the the first thing is the only
reason that it it costs that much money
to fax
fast-track vaccines is because
there is such an onerous
research and development process around
what the fda does and you could probably
do a whole
episode around the the fda problem
that is you know the the fact that
that we have this dual mandate on the
part of the fda of safety and efficacy
um
that this both that these both are in
question
and that that you have stage multiple
stage trials
it takes 10 to 15 years to get a
compound to market
normally and so that's one problem the
other problem is that you have
this uh you know eyepiece ip squatting
on compounds
anyway there's all kinds of you know
public choice issues
which is you know rent seeking issues
interest seeking i guess you could say
if you're not familiar with that
terminology
around medical compounds that come to
the market
in my view there would be there are a
lot there will be a lot cheaper more
effective
mechanism market mechanisms for
determining
whether something works and whether it
is safe then we currently have the
regime we currently have
i think a great in great measure a lot
of the costs of
the things we enjoy the good things we
enjoy from pharma
are a result of that the regulatory
apparatus okay so that's one thing
so if we were to streamline that process
i don't think it would cost as much
money to get to
to vaccines i also don't think we would
have a loss in safety
but uh since that that is a currently a
monopoly then we have to
raise money to fast track it right so
the regulation begets more regulation
begets more subsidy
in that case in the alternative universe
that that would i would like to see
you would have a situation where much of
that is dismantled and you'd have
you'd have a different perhaps more
market-based mechanism for this
and then you would be able to tokenize
compounds
what is tokenization anyway if p anybody
ever heard of a digital ledger knows
that they're
or you're able to find uh investment
mechanisms and we're
we're you know we're in the trough of
disillusionment right now for blockchain
and associated cryptocurrencies
but you know we went through the trough
of disillusionment with the internet in
the year 2000 2001. so everybody's
familiar with that
that being said we're going to start to
see a
much more improved state of affairs for
ways of uh collaborative investing
in certain kinds of things now let's say
that okay max is not going to get his
wild crazy
you know wild wild west social
singularity
way of supporting something like this
through some kind of tokenization effort
which would give people uh a bunch of
different individuals
an investment stake in some compound or
some
vaccine or a trip to mars for that
matter you could tokenize a trip to mars
rather than
taking our tax dollars and giving it to
elon musk
without our permission um i think these
tokenization efforts
are tremendous in in the way that they
could work
but but let's just say that okay i don't
want to be so doctrinaire in my
my sort of market anarchism let's let's
think of a
different like a middle ground i think
contests
would be a much better mechanism for
doing that where you have
you know maybe some very very basic r d
support for something
and otherwise you you know the winners
the first uh past the post to
who are able to um find safe and
effective
vaccine get a really big prize and that
that
incentive is much better than just
subsidizing companies who may or may not
come up with a vaccine and do it in time
yep and of course there has been some
work there darpa has run some very
interesting experiments the x prize guys
and i agree with you that you know put
out a 20 billion dollar prize for a
quite high standard vaccine would have
been a good idea
probably too late now because they've
gone the route of just throwing billions
at lots of different companies and
hoping something works and
yeah it's the spaghetti against the wall
uh technique and i i just
that introduces so many bad precedents
um
and also it's just piling more and more
problems on to
what we're already seeing with this
quote-unquote stimulus that we recently
went through in these stages of stimulus
that
that were just showering resources on
these big companies
just complete political nonsense half of
them it it's
it's really quite staggering the kind of
the way
political allocation works the horse
trading the
the the corruption it's it's awful
there's not even a quasi quasi-market
mechanism involved there there's no
connection
between the output of value and the
input of
of basically debt dollars because we're
in such deep debt that it doesn't
it doesn't even make sense to talk about
it in terms of taxpayer dollars anymore
you stimulated some thinking there let
me throw one out i'm going to try to
channel
max max borders here on vaccines
prize idea is cool but let's say you had
to have a high safety and a high
efficacy
what about we got a little even more
radical a little bit more post
singularity in here
and we instead said any company could
put out
a vaccine but it must be
radically transparent at the level of
insurance that it has
so in other words you know my buddy
brian hanley
made his vaccine in his basement right
he actually he's actually a viral
vaccinologist and he knows how to do
this
and he might convince a few rich guys in
silicon valley to pledge parts of their
fortune the way lloyd's of london
works and you know he gets elon musk to
say i'll put up five billion dollars of
indemnity and he gets bill gates to put
up 10 billion right
he says hey there's hardly any risk here
this thing is safe as and people
look and
see his radically transparent efficacy
results and they see he's got 20 billion
dollars worth of indemnification
and then you just make your own decision
on when to go forward and take the
vaccine based on
a radically transparent efficacy results
and
you know hard promises of indemnity in
the lloyds of london fashion
i love it jim i love it um i i think
that's a fantastic idea and
i'm gonna steal it for my next book feel
free
if you'll permit me i i think it's a
fantastic idea
i think these this kind of idea of
insurance can
really does have a lot of interesting
applications um there's another
immediate social problem where it could
work and that is requiring
police officers to have civil insurance
of course you'd have to remove qualified
immunity
from police and make them directly
liable for any injuries that
that happen on the job but then they
have to also carry insurance
and if you hurt too many people and you
get sued too many times your
insurance will be unaffordable or you'll
get dropped
that's another application i think is
really interesting and it's interesting
it's actually
it does exist my brother recently
retired after a long and fairly glorious
career in federal law enforcement my dad
was a cop
washington dc for his whole career one
of my favorite cousins was
a cop in prince george's county maryland
sort of infamous in its day for bad
policing
but anyway i talked to my brother about
this he's very smart and hangs out in
all the online
cop theory venues and he pointed out
that
federal law enforcement already requires
this he as a
federal law enforcement officer was
required to carry a certain amount of
indemnity insurance
and as you'd point out the price was
artificially low because of qualified
immunity
so that's an obvious way to get started
though of course we have to look at the
bad faith attempts to exploit that right
if there were these big pools or money
around there'd be all kinds of false
charges and there'd be all kinds of
settlements by the insurance company and
bad faith would reign so we would also
need some other institutional
reforms such as one i've always liked is
the british
style of litigation where loser pays
both sides legal costs right
so you make a false claim uh violation
of your rights by the police
well you're perfectly able to litigate
that but if you're wrong
you pay both sides legal defense and
then you say well the poor person on the
street
can't afford to take that risk i say
well how about this let's allow the
syndication of claims
right so there could be a marketplace of
claims so i'm
mary smith who was beaten up by the cops
and can prove it but i got no money to
sue and i don't want to risk my
grandmother's house
to you know fund the litigation so
instead i take my
video camera output put it up on a
marketplace say who wants to back my
lawsuit
and how much do you want as your
component of the settlement right
and an equilibrium point comes that she
gets two million dollars worth of
litigation by offering
30 of what she collects and then goes
after them
i think that's another market style
reform which then
tends to mitigate the bad faith
shakedown which could occur otherwise
that's also really good yeah yep yep
i'm channeling max borders here i'm
thinking this way i just need to call
you up and
get more of your ideas and steal them
yeah feel free
i love to just get my ideas out in the
world of course i'll credit you jim
matt fine by me either way let's move on
here unfortunately as i mentioned
there's so much
in this book i mean we could go on for
hours let's switch directions a little
bit you talk quite a bit and quite
eloquently
about how for the last i don't know at
least 10 000 years and it may be more
like 50 000 years
hierarchy has been the main way that we
have organized
collaboration both in states or state
like things
and in commerce and there may be some
opportunities to move towards
new open systems approaches as we'd say
in the game b world
things that are network-centric
self-organizing
and decentralized as opposed to command
and control hierarchical structures
and you give some examples maybe talk a
little bit about that maybe particularly
in the context of
governance of work because i think
that's something that a lot of people
feel
alienated from the way you know
traditional command and control
structures have operated yeah and i want
to um i want to
another show notes kind of note here for
your listeners
i want to encourage everybody to if you
aren't already familiar with the work
of brian robertson or tom thomason
both of them have done really
interesting
things respectively when it comes to
transitioning out of hierarchy
in terms of the way the firm is
organized
brian uh has certainly brought
this kind of reform and by the way i
also i work with a man who is um
out in california named chris roofer who
he runs a tomato empire and his
his entire looks like 2 000 employees
like
i think five tomato processing plants
and just
just a fleet of trucks that take
tomatoes to these processing plants so
if you ever eat spaghetti or anything
you can find
chris uh chris roofer's products um he's
a mentor of mine he's a brilliant man
and his whole organization is completely
non-hierarchical or you might think of
it as as being
the shallowest of hierarchies which is
to say chris
and the rest but because chris owns the
the organization and
there's a certain amount of heft that
comes with that but in any case chris
has an organization that is completely
self-managed which is to say there is no
management hierarchy at all this is kind
of a foreign concept to most of us
unless you're familiar with holacracy
and brian robertson is
the one who came up with the idea of
holacracy and it is really an
internal social operating system that
allows firms
to self-govern and self-organize
without managers bosses and the like
and really the this transformation of
the rules and protocols within
organization is allowing people to
live their work days in a much more
participatory way
with a sense of ownership and agency and
efficacy
that people who are handed tasks and
told what to do within
the traditional firms are not i actually
think
systems like holacracy might actually be
able to scale to the level of society
i don't know that to be the case and
just like jim with your liquid democracy
i would want to see
some test cases of you know scale beyond
beyond a company to something bigger to
some bigger
you know part of a jurisdiction but
holacracy allows us
systems within systems governance
localized governance
of hollandic systems that nevertheless
are bound together under a single
i guess you call it telos or mission so
the mission is the boss in these
organizations
and i'm i find these these really
interesting and really promising
both for the fact that when you work in
a holocratic organization
you feel less put upon by people who are
basically type a [ __ ] i mean you
know there is that dynamic when you go
to work sometimes
but it also resolves it puts tensions in
the workplace front and center to be
resolved and adjudicated on a
on a daily basis rather than
passing the buck or or or relying on
managers to settle conflicts
and make decisions on your behalf so
that that's one really promising piece
of it
the other i think goes to what you call
corporate
gigantism okay or gigantism
and that is um this is tom thomason's
piece he's developed
uh you can find encode e-n-c-o-d-e
dot org is a an organization that helps
companies set up in a way where they use
the old llc model
to develop companies that are not your
traditional
corporate hierarchies the traditional
corporate hierarchy is
baked into the tax code what encode does
and tom tom's team does is they
essentially adapt what we have
in llc's to function more like
cooperatives okay but there is d
more dynamism with respect to
remuneration and also dynamic shares of
the corporation
that track more closely to value input
and more closely to how the rest of the
team perceives you
so it's not a cooperative in the classic
sense of like a michelle balance
although
that's probably also true michelle does
great work in
in this space but there tends to be this
default
to democracy with with cooperatives that
just that's kind of shitty and it
doesn't really work
and it tends to you know lapse into kind
of corporate socialism
of one form or the other whereas these
dynamic systems
of both internal governance like
holocracy and the way that the company
is
formed allow people to become dynamic
shareholders
as they continue to work and create
value
so that there's no boss who has like
twenty percent of the you know
you know uh 55 percent of the company do
do whatever they want and run rough shot
over everybody
and become rich beyond their you know
anyone's wildest dreams
in instead what you have is a multiple
participatory arrangement where people
can grow rich together
that means you're never going to have a
jeff bezos but you're also going to have
a much much bigger middle class
if these kind of dynamically operated
and designed organizations were to be
propagated i guess you could say so
that's a whole lot it's it goes
it goes quite deep uh but for now i'd
say holacracy
and uh the encode model of the the
development of the corporation
if those two things could predominate we
would we would solve a lot of social
problems
starting with corporate [ __ ] yep
they're what i
often call game a right
game
and i'll confess to having been one back
in the day and a pretty damn good one at
it
bless you for that it's a broken system
we don't want to go there i'm glad to
hear about this
encode idea because you know i've been
interested
in cooperatives but you point out you
know the simple cooperative model
doesn't really work
right and it needs more juice to it and
so
there is a lot of work going on in
hybrid cooperatives and
this encode may be one variant on that i
certainly want to look at it
i was also very interested in learning
about this morningstar company i'd never
heard of it
and i did a little research on it and
there's a cool article
in the harvard business review of all
places about
gary hamel yeah gary hamill very famous
high dollar management guru it's called
let's fire all the managers actually
quite cool
on the other hand as i dug deeper trying
to find out more
there ain't much to find out there are
very few articles
almost nothing published on it since
2012.
they used to have morningstar did a
self-management institute
the website no longer works they have a
facebook
page about self management hasn't been
updated since 2015.
so i tell you the backstory on that
there's a guy named paul greene jr
who actually is a professor uh at the
the b school here in
in austin at ut austin now who used to
work
as the head of the self-management
institute and when he went off to get
his phd
in management he
left morningstar and uh they didn't
really reconstitute it after that point
and so the the idea was they wanted to
spin this off
as as a kind of consultancy model
but uh i think it never just got off the
ground and and
chris thought that it chris roofer the
the the founder
thought that it would be best just to
focus on the core competency which is
making good tomatoes
i think that's rather a shame and i'm
i'm close to chris i talk to him
nearly every week because i work for him
on a contract basis
and i just think he's an incredible man
i'm i'm working on
ghost writing a book for him as well and
i think it's just an amazing story
that this company runs this way
and it's not perfect look nothing is we
always have to ask as compared to what
but when one does the comparative
analysis and you actually talk to the
people who work there
and some of them are seasonal workers
from from central america you know
but there is a real culture of dignity
and
collaboration there that's almost like
an emergent phenomenon
of just respecting two basic rules which
is don't ever threaten anybody with
their job
or don't ever threaten anybody period
and
operate with integrity in other words
honor what your word what you say you're
going to do
and from that they have some basic sort
of organizational processes that they
implement
but it's not even it's not as
complicated as holocracy
i think holacracy is harder to learn and
more promising
in in its scope but as from a standpoint
of being a heuristic and it's also
probably more efficient
but from the standpoint of a heuristic
it's
it's more difficult to master uh
morningstar being much simpler so
there's all kinds of experiments and
governance going on right now at the
level of the corporation and if these
really take hold
i think people will slowly start to
disabuse themselves
of these hierarchical models that
currently run the country yep i agree
and i think this is a huge area for
experimentation and
work would your morningstar guy be
interested in coming on the jim rutt
show and tell us what he does you mean
chris the founder
yeah oh yeah i'm sure he would i'll i'll
be happy to
to talk to him and i think you'll find
him a fascinating man
yeah i would love it i mean you know
hell as an entrepreneur i've helped
start 17 companies i know what it's like
and some of them were more humane than
others probably none of them were as
humane as this so i'd love to have a
conversation with them
you did mention holacracy and i looked
at that pretty carefully back in 2013
when it was first starting to get some
play
and i kind of said hmm maybe
right and i was glad to hear it was
tried a place like zappos but i
just did some research over the last
couple days and discovered that
zappos has kind of backed away from it
or at least
changed it a lot and as i suspected it
turned out to have too much overhead to
be really
good in the long term and that doesn't
surprise me you know these are first
assays these are first attempts to do
things
and you know the key is to not be
doctrinaire or ideological about them
rather to
you know be ideological write down an
idea and
try it but when it needs to be improved
improve it
i do wish there were more literature
about this wish there were a
self-management institute
that would share the learnings from
these various experiments
because it's going to be a really
important part of crafting what comes
next
actually getting to the point as we
claim in game b which we haven't proved
which is that you know organizations run
on this basis
in a self-organizing network-centric
decentralized fashion operating and
honesty and good faith and with a
significant though not total amount of
economic sharing
will actually be able to out-compete
game a companies
we actually have to do that we haven't
yet and these experiments are really
really important in figuring out what
works and what doesn't
honestly jim i'll share with you i think
that is the sink what you just said is
the single most important thing we can
do for social change in this
in this world right now and it seems
crazy to think about what corporations
what like what why would that be
with all that we have going on with the
pandemic with you know people toppling
statues in the streets and burning
portland down and this that and the
other would the transformation of the
corporation
make a hill of beans to anything but i i
really do
think that when people spend eight hours
out of their day
creating value for each other
that is a linchpin if we can transform
organizations in such a way to be much
more humane
participatory efficient effective all of
that stuff as you said
it's it also shows the way for
how we can organize ourselves in other
domains and are currently
not that's the promise of it let me also
give you a quick
note on the book reinventing
organizations
is the name of the book they profile
morningstar
and other organizations like zappos as
well as ricardo zimmler's
outfit i think is in there down in down
in brazil there's a lot of these kind of
organizations
and they're called teal organizations
more broadly
the teal organization trope comes from
teal and
in integral theory which is second tier
which is to understand complex systems
as emergent phenomena
and not as planned that leap in
cognition is known as teal and integral
integral theory so he calls them teal
organizations and this book
really does give you a good idea about
all of the possible variations or at
least it parameterizes
the variations up to this point in what
can be
thought of as self-managed organizations
damage is that book out or are you guys
writing it or what's the deal
yeah that's that's yeah it's reinventing
organizations has been out since about
2015 i think now i think we're on the
same page that these are very important
but i would add at least in my view
these things
are substantially pissing up hill unless
we also reform
money and finance and also taxes
because there's a reason that
socioeconomic evolution in game a has
produced
gigantic companies that do all they can
to extract monopoly rent through
corrupting the political process and
just getting
big and if we don't have a money finance
and taxation system
to level the playing field so that
people can't mine
giant network effects and everybody
over the opportunity for these
reinvented organizations the barrier the
the activation energy they need
gets really high and it may be so high
that it's really hard for them to
succeed other than in niches
and of course you write a lot in the
book about bitcoin personally i'm not
i don't like bitcoin i think it's got
lots and lots of problems
but i do believe that one of the great
things about this epoch
is that people have finally realized
that fractional reserve banking money
managed by central bankers was not
brought down from mount sinai
by moses and that there's lots and lots
and lots of design space and money and
finance
and taxation that we haven't even
started to explore yet and it's
really good that we are oh yeah no
there's no doubt about it i mean
bitcoin is the eximplar because it's the
first one and it itself
is a continuously evolving uh both
ecosystem
of of programmers but also in its
properties
uh you know it's gotten faster it's more
scalable now
there it has a lot of problems but it
also has a lot of competitors
so if you see this as a an evolutionary
fitness landscape
this you know distributed finance but
also cryptocurrencies
it really you know we did have to go
through a dark time where people were
throwing a bunch of money at a bunch of
trash
and they got burned by the market you
know they had skin in the game and they
lost their asses
but now now that there's that is shaking
out a little bit
people are starting to realize what had
staying power what had utility
and phase two or the second wave of this
stuff is going to be
really interesting because we're going
to start to see not only how it
transforms
everyday users because that was a really
that was a problem too
a lot of these these geeks don't know
how to design for
ux for ordinary people so they were
designing for themselves
and that meant that you had some really
clunky software and some
really difficult you know security
management
issues that frankly for someone who has
a little bit of a right brain like i do
i found off-putting even though i was a
cheerleader for all these things
but that soon is going to change because
the ux designers are going to come come
on board and then we're going to see
rapid adoption
and when we see rapid adoption we're
going to start to i hope
invert the process of what is known as
concentrated benefits and dispersed
costs
and that's to say if it becomes
more beneficial to own a cryptocurrency
than to own a traditional fiat currency
we could see a real change in the game
there because
there will be such rapid adoption and
it'll be so hard to
to have an enforcement mechanism it may
be that it's game over for the
system of central banking but i tell you
what they're doing their hardest to
clamp down on anything that resembles
competition
and they're being very effective about
it right now
yep and i will say for some good reasons
because unfortunately
the design of most of the current
cryptocurrencies
basically means they're only good for
one thing which well two things
one is they're excellent for payment of
ransoms
and the other thing is they're good for
criminal transactions right
especially if you had a blender in the
middle to get something closer to
anonymity
and they're not really good for much
anything else they take too long to
settle the transaction costs are too
high
the currencies are unstable you know i
could go a long list of things that are
wrong with
most of the current currencies but as
you say people are learning and are
evolving and they're second there's
third and fourth generation currencies
and hopefully
some of them will learn the lessons from
the first generation though i do believe
as a matter of principle that the whole
family of
truly trustless allegedly trustless
currencies is a big mistake that the
value of
radical trustlessness is way smaller
than people think it is
and it's also false because in reality
at least in everyone i've seen at the
end of the day you end up having to
trust a small
group of software developers and they're
the ones that fundamentally are the
governance and they're not really held
accountable
etc and yet radical trustlessness comes
at an insane price
the last time i did the numbers which is
around 2015 the cost of proof of work
in bitcoin amounted to about seven
percent of the market cap of bitcoin
per year which is insane you know even
our
fractional reserve currency system which
is grossly inefficient
central banker mediated fractional
reserve currency system
has overheads on the order of two
percent per year and so
bitcoin's you know three and a half
times less effective
and is actually much less usable in a
whole bunch of ways so
there's a lot of room to improve but i
do believe that this area should be
explored
absolutely and and getting these
cryptocurrencies to to do these
complicated
problems of solving cryptographic
puzzles and things like that in order to
to be trustless you know these are
there's
all kinds of different competing notions
to how to achieve the same level of
security at a lower price
and it's just it's incredible the rate
at which these
these attempts are being made so you
know disintermediation
happens at different levels of the stack
too by the way
not just at the level of the coders and
what they create but it's also
when you create a network of people that
yeah we might have to rely for a while
on a group of bitcoin coders
but at the level of human interaction
that right there is better than
certain other kinds of transactions so
relativizing
our sense of these different properties
and how they will improve into the
future
following another moore's law type
phenomenon you're right there is
a tremendous promise in it and i think
there will be an inflection point beyond
which it
the game will be over for fiat
currencies they'll have to
either be radically totalitarian in
their approach to reining them in
or they'll just have to change the way
they tax
and maintain their monopolies
it'll be interesting and at least in the
u.s there has been some attempt
to clean up the marketplace of you know
the bad and absolutely fraudulent
cryptocurrencies but it is interesting
in the u.s it's legal
it's clearly legal to operate
alternative currencies which is actually
a hopeful thing
i think for the us i i agree yeah and i
i
you know for the moment uh we it it is
legal you can trade them
and uh the problem is is that you can't
create them anymore
in fact you know ethereum and
really ethereum and bitcoin were
grandfathered in but
i i was uh one of the things i was
hoping to do
with social evolution the little
non-profit that you mentioned at the
beginning of the show
was to create a consensus mechanism
where people could
be mutually supportive in their uh
entrepreneurial projects and ventures at
the very early stages
and we tried to come up with a consensus
mechanism on on a blockchain
and it seemed like it would be a really
interesting
well not a yeah a really interesting way
of
dispersing funds uh held in common by a
group of people
with similar aims it functions sort of
like a mutual aid society except for
entrepreneurs
in this approach i started talking to
some real experts in the space
and they were super excited about the
idea but they said
max you're going to have to move to
another country to do this and he
listed about six different regulatory
agencies that would have precluded our
doing this project
so you know i've got kids
i've got a family my parents are still
alive
i i don't want to move to malta to be
able to pull this off or to
switzerland you know that is an
incredible barrier
the fact that i'm still in meat space
meant that uh you know the
this idea of subversive innovation that
i preach you know very hard
that doesn't mean i haven't been a
victim of of of the you know sort of
hierarchical state that is going to look
out for its interest and it's going to
mute the aspirations of certain kinds of
entrepreneurs basically you have to be
well funded and you have to be
absolutely cocksure of yourself to want
to
move countries to continue the
revolution but some people are doing
that and let's hope there's just enough
enough to continue doing it and and
people working on this stuff in other
countries
to pull it off but i would say i would
say the
the regulatory apparatus of the state is
is quite potent quite powerful right now
and it's it's
something that i underestimated in about
for sure indeed indeed in fact i had my
own little encounter with it back in
about 2004 i think it was
i got real excited by robin hansen's
idea of opinion marketplaces
and i actually put together a
proto-venture to look into it and hired
an international lawyer to figure out
you know was it legal in the u.s and if
not where this and that the answer came
out the optimal place to do it was the
isle of man
it's and it still is one of the good
ones this this is
really goes to this question of
collective intelligence i think
the things in the vein of hansen's
prediction markets
futarchic systems are you know
they're going to have to experiment with
them but jim that you know i wish you
could have done that because
there's so many interesting things that
we can learn
about the world and we can we can really
improve our
collective intelligence just by making
it
cost something to be wrong
that certainly helps as we know what did
they tell you to do just that
the isle of man was the only way to pull
it off and you were going to run it
right
the isle of man i could have put up with
and i wouldn't have run it myself i
would have hired someone to do it
but they also pointed out the very
onerous
criminal penalties for money laundering
should you try to repatriate your
winnings back to the u.s and at that
point i
said that right i'm willing to lose
my money but i'm not willing to get
thrown in jail for five years for doing
something which i believe is good for
the world right so i just said all
this i'm not willing to
get entangled with money laundering laws
right it's ridiculous like you can go
you can go to the to the new york stock
exchange and
buy shares in the in the future
performance of some
company which is gambling but you're not
allowed to
invest in what your perception of truth
assets are
yeah it'd be a huge as robin has pointed
out it would be hugely useful in lots of
ways particularly if the market got big
i mean it exists today but it's tiny not
big enough for the signal to have high
fidelity
but if there were i don't know 10
billion dollars invested in these
opinion marketplaces
those signals would be useful to
everybody to help them make better
decisions
yeah that's that's right even if you
even if you didn't have any skin in the
game
and you didn't have any money you could
certainly look at the performance of
these
i don't know what you want to call them
bets wagers right
bets or wagers over time to to see uh
how they're holding up
it it adds a layer to that poparian
model we were talking
about earlier that's that's staggering
in its implications
yep it is interesting that nobody has
ever seen fit to see the importance of
this
and allow it which gets me to probably
the most radical idea you have in the
book
which the book is full of radical ideas
and that's the idea of getting around
problems like this
through allowing multiple sovereignties
so for instance you know one could agree
to be bound by the u.s
law on things like opinion marketplaces
or
the ideas you were doing there for
startup entrepreneurs with the ability
of mutual support mutual
help etc or you could choose to make
yourself subject to estonian law
right or the isle of man talk a little
bit about this radical idea about how we
break out of the box of geography when
it comes to at least part
of our interactions with the state
yeah i think um you know earlier jim we
were talking about
about federalism and the idea this the
idea
there is what is known as
polycentric law but the idea of
polycentric law means that it's still
this idea that law and the enforcement
of law
is is coupled in some way to
some swath of territory when we think
about
the history of sort of conquest and
power it's easy to understand how
law has come to be associated with
territory but
we're living in an age where
technological advance
and systems of co-creation and
collaboration cross
geographies you're sitting now some i
think in on vacation
in pennsylvania i'm here in texas and
we're
in a sense collaborating on your show
texas law applies to me pennsylvania law
applies to you
and that is a very sort of jurisdiction
couple to territory kind of phenomenon
there's this old uh there's this old
liberal liberal in the
in the in the classical sense belgian
man named
dupuis who was writing on the in about
1860 and he asked the question
why is it that rules should be coupled
to territories
and in fact it really doesn't make any
sense he he said
why don't we think of it as a situation
where we could
basically go to a registration office
which in those times that's what it
would be necessary and you would
essentially register
for your for your rules of governance
okay other people would do the same and
then you would use essentially the
common law to adjudicate between those
different jurisdictional forms but they
wouldn't have much to do with territory
and of course you have to think about
things that are
certain kinds of goods or certain kinds
of things that have something to do with
territory like your water rights and
things like that earlier
but otherwise most things that we do in
this life
especially these days with so much of
our lives being online
don't really have anything to do with
terra firma and they have everything to
do with the rules of the game
and as you know i i've tried to
emphasize in this conversation and in
the book if experimentation with new
rules of the game
is going to help hasten this
lateralization of human behavior we're
going to need a set of protocols to do
so when you're going to need to
experiment with those
those protocols polyarchy or panarky
allows us to do that that anarchy is his
term
uh for this this phenomenon which is
you can essentially i could say okay i
really like the singaporean healthcare
system
so the singaporean healthcare system
allows you to have a large medical
savings accounts and they have a small
single-payer portion that keeps you from
going bankrupt if you have an expensive
medical procedure but basically
everybody pays out of their accounts and
these are interest-bearing accounts
so people have these great incentives to
watch their spending
well i think that's a great idea maybe i
should be able to adopt that model
rather than the american model which is
governed by
the the aca but here where i'm not i'm
not
you know just buying into a a certain
kind of product i'm buying a
system i'm participating in a system
and those systems that cloud governance
can have conflicts with other people but
those can be adjudicated
as we say with the common law so there's
really interesting ideas of the
decoupling
of terra firma with rules and that's
that's really probably the most radical
idea in the book and i think that's
where we're headed in the social
singularity
very cool i mean i agree with you that
was i mean i could argue about the pros
and cons of this but it's truly an
innovative idea
and as you all have heard from reading
this book this book is full of all kinds
of interesting ideas packed into a nice
compact package so
i'd recommend if you're interested in
things we talked about go out and buy it
the social singularity by max borders
thank you very much max for a very
interesting conversation
i look forward to tipping a few back
with you jim okay we got to do it next
time we're in austin or be it up to
virginia
hell yes all right
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared james consulting
music by tom mueller at
modernspacemusic.com